<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://rcrtss.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://rcrtss.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-04-27T15:56:27+00:00</updated><id>https://rcrtss.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>My personal portfolio based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">notes on classical planning</title><link href="https://rcrtss.github.io/blog/2025/hashnode-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="notes on classical planning"/><published>2025-04-27T14:24:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-27T14:24:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rcrtss.github.io/blog/2025/hashnode-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rcrtss.github.io/blog/2025/hashnode-1/"><![CDATA[<p>This post collects some notes and key concepts on classical planning. At the end of this post, you will know: what Planning is in AI, how to define a planning problem and some of the most popular approaches for tackling these problems.</p> <p>Before we dive into the details, imagine this situation.</p> <p>It’s a weekday at 7:00 am. Your alarm rings and you start your routine—shower, dress, coffee, brush teeth. You do this automatically, without thinking. But eventually, you reach a point where you can’t continue on autopilot, and you need to think about your next moves. You need to <strong>plan</strong>!</p> <blockquote> <p><em>Okay, ready for work. Now, should you take the bus or go by car? oh wait… you don’t own a car. It’ll be bus or subway. The bus will get you there faster, but… it’s already late, so the bus may have left, and no time to wait for the next one.</em></p> </blockquote> <p><img src="/assets/img/blog-1-1.jpeg" alt="Planning task in daily life" style="display: block; margin: 0 auto; max-width: 100%; height: auto;"/></p> <blockquote> <p><em>Got it: get to the bus stop first, if the bus is there just take it, otherwise, walk to the subway station and take the Line 5, after four stops, switch to Line 3. Three more stops and it will leave you next to your workplace. With that you’ll hopefully get there in about 30 minutes, just in time. Let’s go!</em></p> </blockquote> <p>By going through that thought process, you just defined a <strong>planning problem</strong> and found a <strong>course of action</strong> to achieve your <strong>goal</strong>. Easy.</p> <p>Let’s try to divide this simple problem into different components, with a focus on <strong>PDDL (Planning Domain Definition Language)</strong>, which we will define further in this post.</p> <h3 id="state-space-representation"><strong>State-Space Representation</strong></h3> <h3 id="states">States</h3> <p>A given <strong>state</strong> of the world can be fully represented with a collection of <strong>variables</strong>.</p> <p>In our example, our initial state may be, for example:</p> <ul> <li>InMyHouse(me) = True</li> <li>HaveCar(me) = False</li> <li>Late(me) = True</li> </ul> <p>If we decide to go to the bus stop first, then we take the action of walking to the bus stop (assuming it is a legal action from the initial state). The result of this action will lead to a <strong>resulting state</strong> which could be characterized by these variable values:</p> <ul> <li>InMyHouse(me) = False</li> <li>AtBusStop(me) = True</li> </ul> <p>Now, to know which action to take next, we may depend on other variables, such as:</p> <ul> <li>AtBusStop(bus) = True</li> </ul> <p>If this <strong>precondition</strong> is fulfilled, it is feasible for me to take the action: <em>TakeBus</em>.</p> <p>We can think of the states as the nodes in our state-space graph, and we can move between states by</p> <h3 id="actions">Actions</h3> <h3 id="preconditions-and-effects">Preconditions and Effects</h3> <h3 id="initial-state">Initial State</h3> <h3 id="goal-state">Goal State</h3> <h3 id="finding-a-plan">Finding a Plan</h3> <h2 id="so-what-is-planning">So, What <strong>Is</strong> Planning?</h2> <p>In our daily lives, we use the word <strong><em>planning</em></strong> to refer to the process of deciding which <strong>actions</strong> to take to achieve a specific <strong>goal</strong> in the future.</p> <p>In AI, we can think about it in a very similar way. The basic idea is to figure out an achievable sequence of actions that will lead us to a desired state. Of course, there are many situations where the only important thing is not just getting to that state, but also doing so <strong>optimally</strong>.</p> <p>This could mean two things: that the computation to find that sequence of actions is done in an <strong>optimal amount of time</strong> with <strong>optimal use of computation resources</strong>, or that the sequence of actions found to achieve our goal has the <strong>lowest possible cost</strong>. Most of the time, both optimalities are highly desirable.</p> <h2 id="classical-planning">Classical Planning</h2> <p>Remember how we described our <em>real world</em> and its characteristics? For many planning problems we do not need all of that complexity to find an acceptable solution, and in those cases we can simplify the problem considerably. The field called <strong>Classical Planning</strong> considers a simplified <strong>environment</strong> that has the following characteristics:</p> <ul> <li>💡 <strong>Discrete:</strong> variables in a certain state can be True, False or even numeric, but always discrete</li> <li>🎯 <strong>Deterministic</strong>: when a given an action is taken (or not), the outcome is predictable and reproducible, with no randomness involved</li> <li><strong>🧊 Static:</strong> the state will not change if the agent does not perform any action</li> <li>👀 <strong>Fully observable</strong>: when the agent has full knowledge of the whole problem</li> </ul> <p>The standard of <em>Planning Domain Definition Language</em> (PDDL) comes into the picture to help us solve these types of problems. Let’s take a look at what PDDL has to offer.</p> <h2 id="planning-domain-definition-language">Planning Domain Definition Language</h2> <p><strong>PDDL</strong> for short, came as a response to limitations of logical agents to solve planning problems. It was developed in 1998 as an attempt to standardise the different planning domain and problem solving languages.</p> <p>PDDL has been extended ever since it was first developed, and more robust and complex versions of this standard are used to find solutions to other <strong>non-classical</strong> domains. Let’s focus then on the basic PDDL that will be sufficient to help us with simple <strong>classical planning</strong> problems.</p> <p>In PDDL, every <strong>state</strong> of the world can be represented with a collection of <strong>variables</strong>, and these states transform into other states when an <strong>action</strong> (from the available actions in the current state) is taken. Each aspect of the world that may change when some action is taken are called <strong>fluents</strong>.</p> <h3 id="predicates">Predicates</h3> <h3 id="action-schemas">Action Schemas</h3> <h3 id="problem-definition">Problem Definition</h3> <h2 id="algorithms-for-classical-planning-in-other-post---just-a-summary-and-mention-other-post">Algorithms for Classical Planning (in other post?) - Just a summary and mention other post</h2> <p>Forward state space, backward state space, boolean, heuristics, plangraph and partial order planning.</p> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <h2 id="appendix">Appendix</h2> <h3 id="about-domain">About Domain</h3> <p>First of all, let’s discuss why I <strong>did not</strong> include in the problem at the beginning of this post all the other actions we <strong>know</strong> are necessary to accomplish our plan. For example, things like: <em>walk to the door, open the door, cross the doorway, (…) cross the street, walk to the bus stop, wait 5 minutes</em>.</p> <p>We can see why all of these actions are indeed necessary to accomplish our goal. We could even break it down further: <em>take 5 steps north-east, then 2 steps east,</em> <strong><em>and then</em></strong> <em>open the door</em>.</p> <p>And further: <em>move your right leg upwards with an acceleration of…</em> Well, you get the point.</p> <p>And so, why did I exclude all those actions from my plan? Simple: for this situation, those actions don’t concern me. I already know how to do them or I’ll figure them out as I go. What I did <strong>not</strong> know was which route to take and what means of transport to use to get to work. That’s why I consider only the actions and variables that were <strong>relevant</strong> for that problem. In other words, I defined and constrained the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">domain</code>.</p> <h3 id="about-our-world">About Our World</h3> <p>The real world is complex, and we have limited computing resources to find the right plan. To surpass these limitations, we may want to simplify the whole problem statement. But before that, lets describe some of the complexities of our world.</p> <p>Whether you’re on your way to work, at a party, or on vacation, in the <strong>real world</strong> you will encounter <strong>uncertainty</strong>. This is because <strong>our world</strong> is intrinsically uncertain, or in other words, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">non-deterministic</code>.</p> <p>For example, while searching for a solution to our planning problem, we’ve considered the possibility that the bus (which was our first option) could’ve been delayed, causing us to arrive late to work. In this sense, having a <em>“Plan B”</em> may have been a smart move when we already know that the possibility exists. But we cannot account for <strong>every</strong> external variable, and coutnless obstacles could get on our way: rain, protests, traffic, flat tires, you name it. What’s more, even if we could account for all of it, we would still need to deal with that uncertainty in an appropriate way (that would increases the complexity of the problem though, and we are not quite ready for that yet).</p> <p>Our world is also <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">dynamic</code>. You may expect that, even if you stop acting, if you sit down and do nothing everything around you will keep changing. The state of the world will be constantly changing, regardless of your inaction.</p> <p>Our world is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">analog</code>. We may forget this one at times, but we do not go from 7:00am to 7:01am just like that. We could split that minute in half and get 7:00:30am. And between 30’’ and 31’’ there is a 30’‘30’’’, and we could continue forever. The same goes for almost any physical variable that we can imagine. The real world is not limited to 1’s and 0’s.</p> <p>Lastly, our world is <strong>huge</strong>. We cannot see everything happening everywhere. From our own perspective, our world is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">partially observable</code>.</p> <p>All together, <em>we live in a</em> <strong><em>non-deterministic</em></strong>, <strong><em>dynamic</em></strong>, <strong><em>analog</em></strong> <em>and</em> <strong><em>partially observable</em></strong> <em>world, and there is nothing we can do about it</em>.</p> <p>As you may have guessed, this makes things <strong>much</strong> more complicated. Luckily, we can always find ways to simplify our view of the world to find solutions that will also work for our complex reality.</p> <p>Once we have simplified a planning problem, we can use <strong>Classical Planning</strong> techniques to <strong>find ways to achieve our goals</strong>. We will cover some of the basic concepts of this topic in this and following post.</p> <h3 id="about-this-post">About This Post</h3> <p>The goal is to collect some of the most important concepts on <strong>Classical Planning</strong>, focusing on popular techniques to tackle this kind of problems. The information in this post is based on my personal notes from the <strong>Automated Planning</strong> course in the <a href="https://www.udacity.com/school/artificial-intelligence">AI Nanodegree from Udacity</a>. Most of the content is taken from this course and the book <em>Artificial Intelligence: A Modern Approach</em> by <em>S. Russell and P. Norvig, Fourth Edition</em> -I am not claiming any of it as my own.</p> <p>The objective of this article is to share an accessible overview of these concepts and hopefully motivate you to continue learning on your own if you find it interesting.</p> <h2 id="sources">Sources</h2> <ul> <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Planning_Domain_Definition_Language">Planning Domain Definition Language - Wikipedia</a></li> <li><a href="https://users.cecs.anu.edu.au/~patrik/pddlman/writing.html">Writing Planning Domains and Problems in PDDL (anu.edu.au)</a></li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="learning"/><category term="ai"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this post collects some notes and key concepts on classical planning]]></summary></entry></feed>